# Amy X. Lu

http://amyxlu.github.io github.com/amyxlu amyxlu@cs.toronto.edu +1-650-776-6772 linkedin.com/in/amyxlu

## Summary

I am a graduate student at the Vector Institute for Artificial Intelligence. I am interested in **developing** biologically-principled machine learning methods, with an emphasis on self-supervised representation learning, generalizability, and biological interpretability. I also serve on SVAI, which organizes research collaborations of genomics/AI researchers and industry partners for patients of understudied diseases.

#### EDUCATION

University of Waterloo

Bachelors of Science, Honours Science, Bioinformatics Option

University of Toronto, Vector Institute

Master's in Computer Science

Stanford University

Visiting Student, Departments of Computer Science and Genetics

Waterloo, Canada
2014 - 2019

Toronto, Canada
Jan 2019 - Present

Palo Alto, USA
Sept 2019 - Present

#### EXPERIENCE

# Stanford University

Palo Alto, USA

Visiting Student Researcher — Domain Adaptation in Regulatory Genomics, Dr. Anshul Kundaje

2019 - Present

• Domain adaptation, ChIP-seq analyses: Using domain adaptation to improve classifier performance and learned genomic sequence features for transcription factor binding when evaluating in a different cellular context.

# University of Toronto/Vector Institute

Toronto, Canada

Masters Student — Representation learning in genomics, Dr. Alan Moses & Dr. Marzyeh Ghassemi 2019 – Present

- Self-supervised learning, natural language processing: Applying contextual word embedding models to learn generalizable and interpretable representations for genomic and proteomic sequences.
- o Generalizability, computer vision: Benchmarked a new "paired cell in-painting" method for out-of-sample generalization in microscopy against various common computer vision algorithms. (NeurIPS 2019 21% acceptance rate; ICML 2019 Self-Supervised Learning Workshop)
- Algorithmic fairness, clinical decision support: Quantitative and qualitative evaluation of bias in "black box" contextual clinical word embeddings, and exploring debiasing methods using adversarial gradient-reversal. (NeurIPS 2019 ML for Healthcare workshop 34% acceptance rate; submitted to FAT\* 2020)

# Harvard Medical School/Boston Children's Hospital

Boston, USA

Research Intern — Machine Learning in Clinical Genomics, Dr. Piotr Sliz

2018 - 2019

- Variant analysis, denoising, genotype-phenotype studies: Applied false-positive variant filtering pipelines and batch effect denoising algorithms to a whole exome (WES) dataset of epilepsy patients.
- Machine learning, dimensionality reduction: Built machine learning models to classify disease phenotype from high-dimensional exome variant data, with emphasis on capturing non-linearities arising from epistasis.

#### University of Waterloo

Waterloo, Canada

Undergraduate Thesis Student — Deep Learning in Regulatory Genomics, Dr. Andrew Doxey

2017 - 2018

- $\circ$  Convolutional neural networks in genomics: Implemented a convolutional neural network which recognizes ATAC-seq region sequences with 91% accuracy.
- o **Interpretability:** Distilled biological knowledge from the "black box" network by reconstructing first-layer features as position-weighted matrices (PWMs) of "motifs" (i.e. genomic patterns). All motifs found statistical matches in JASPAR (database of known motifs).
- Phylogenetics, metagenomic data mining: Used various bioinformatics pipeline tools (HMMER, BLAST, etc.) to understand and discover potential novel toxin homologs in metagenomic databases.
- Self-directed learning: Self-learned deep learning concepts and Python as a biology student.

# École polytechnique fédérale de Lausanne

Lausanne, Switzerland

Research Intern — Molecular Dynamics Simulations, Dr. Matteo Dal Parero

2017

- Molecular dynamics: Contributed three potential findings on enzyme-membrane mechanisms of bacterial "superbugs" using computational molecular dynamics (MD) simulations.
- Automating workflows: Automated workflows and analyzed simulations using R, tcl/tk, and Csh scripts.

# University of Toronto

Toronto, Canada

Research Intern — Data Visualization in Pharmacoepidemiology, Dr. Suzanne Cadarette

2015 - 2017

- **Pharmacoepidemiology:** Took initiative to redesign manual workflows. Contributed two co-authored publications, one poster, and figures for an international epidemiology conference within two months.
- Data visualization: Wrangled data using R and SQL to create animated and interactive co-authorship networks.

#### AWARDS

- NSERC Michael Smith Foreign Supplement: Supports high-calibre Canadian graduate students in pursuing research abroad. Valued at \$6,000.
- Canada Graduate Scholarships-Master's (CGS-M) Award: NSERC federal research grant. Valued at \$17,500.
- Scholarship of Excellence in Research: One of 13 students sponsored for research at EPFL. Valued at CHF 4,500.
- University of Waterloo: Various entrance awards totaling \$6,000.
- Associate of The Royal Conservatory (ARCT): Performer's Diploma in Piano.

#### Publications and Conference Proceedings

- Accepted: Lu AX, Lu AXP, Moses A. The Cells Out of Sample (COOS) dataset and benchmarks for measuring out-of-sample generalization of image classifiers. *Conference on Neural Information Processing Systems* (NeurIPS) 2019.
- Submitted: Zhang H\*, Lu AX\*, Abdalla M, McDermott M, Ghassemi M. Hurtful Words: Quantifying Biases in Clinical Contextual Word Embeddings. Submitted to ACM Conference on Fairness, Accountability, and Transparency (ACM FAT\*). \*Co-first authors.
- Published: Ban J, Tadrous M, Lu AX, Cicinelli EA, Cadarette SM. Diffusion of indirect comparison meta-analytic methods to study drugs: a systematic review and co-authorship network analysis. *BMJ Open*.
- Under revision: Consiglio GP, Maclure M, Lu AX, Cicinelli EA, Ban JK, McCarthy L, Cadarette SM. Guidance documents for the application of Self-controlled Crossover Observational PharmacoEpidemiology (SCOPE) designs are needed: systematic review and animated co-authorship networks. Submitted to Pharmcoepi Drug Saf.

#### Workshop Papers and Poster Presentations

- Accepted: Lu AX\*, Zhang H\*, Abdalla M, McDermott M, Ghassemi M. Hurtful Words: Quantifying Biases in Clinical Contextual Word Embeddings. Hurtful Words: Quantifying Biases in Clinical Contextual Word Embeddings. Poster presentation, NeurIPS 2019 Workshop on Fair ML for Health. \*Co-first authors.
- Accepted: Zhang H\*, Lu AX\*, Abdalla M, McDermott M, Ghassemi M. Hurtful Words: Quantifying Biases in Clinical Contextual Word Embeddings. Hurtful Words: Quantifying Biases in Clinical Contextual Word Embeddings. Extended Abstract, NeurIPS 2019 Workshop on Machine Learning for Healthcare. \*Co-first authors.
- Accepted: Abdalla M, Lu AX, Zhang H, Chen I, Ghassemi M. Quantifying Fairness in a Multi-Group Setting and its Impact in the Clinical Setting. Poster presentation, NeurIPS 2019 Workshop on Fair ML for Health.
- Submitted: Moses A, Lu AX, Lu AXP, Ghassemi M. Transfer Learning vs. Batch Effects: what can we expect from neural networks in computational biology?. *Machine Learning in Computational Biology (MLCB) 2019*.
- Presented: Lu AX, Lu AXP, Moses A. Paired Cell Inpainting: A Multiple-Instance Extension of Self-Supervised Learning for Bioimage Analysis. *Poster presentation*, *ICML 2019 Workshop on Self-Supervised Learning*.
- Presented: Lu AX, Rockowitz S, Poduri A, Sliz P. From data to precision medicine: predictive machine learning models to uncover disease-associated variants. *Poster. Harvard Medical School BCMP Retreat 2019.*
- Submitted: Lu AX, Tam ES. Effect of prophylactic brimonidine on subconjunctival hemorrhage in laser-assisted cataract surgery. Poster abstract. Submitted to American Academy of Ophthalmology 2017.
- Presented: Lu AX, Consiglio GP, Cadarette SM. Dynamic Visualization in Co-Authorship Network Analysis. *Poster presentation*. Leslie Dan Faculty of Pharmacy Undergraduate Research Symposium.
- Presented: McIlroy-Young R, Lu AX, Guenther N, Olarnyk A. A Network Analysis: Did the Arab Spring Impact the Academic Network of Tunisia Between 2010 and 2015? Poster presentation. Knowledge Integration Symposium.

# SERVICE AND ACTIVITIES

- SVAI: Core Team of SVAI, a non-profit connecting patients of rare genomic diseases to the medical/AI research community and industry partners through collaborative research initiatives.
- Residence Don, Velocity Incubator: Leader for the residence program of Canada's most productive start-up incubator; fostered close relations with diverse students to support conduct and mental health crises.
- Tosamaganga Hospital, Tanzania: Supported operations at a rural Tanzanian hospital and shadowed surgical procedures. Expenses were covered by scholarships, fundraising, and part-time tutoring.

#### Teaching

- Teaching Assistant, Genetics: Taught weekly tutorials for BIOL 239 at the University of Waterloo.
- Piano & theory: Taught piano performance (up to RCM 7), RCM music history, and RCM Intermediate Rudiments.
- Tutoring: Tutor for IB Calculus, IB Chemistry, and English.

## Talks

- Vector NLP Talks: Quantifying and Removing Biases in Clinical Contextual Word Embeddings. Co-presenter.
- Harvard Medical School BCMP Retreat 2019: From data to precision medicine: predictive machine learning models to uncover disease-associated variants. *Lightning talk*.

#### HACKATHONS AND PROJECTS

- Chatsense: Mobile chat app using a sentiment analysis machine learning API on voice messages and mapping dominant emotions to emojis, designed for the autistic community. Team project. "Can a Computer Hear How You Feel?" prize: YHacks at Yale.
- Alice: Web login page using a trained facial recognition model to login to online banking without passwords, designed for dementia patients. *Team project. Desjardin prize: ConUHacks III.*